so one that was awesome that was
fantastic and wildly beautiful and so
important I mean so important you know
and you know this is the place and we're
gonna be dialoguing more in this both on
the the second person topic from I think
that was week
five right and and on this this paradox
topic which is one of our core grounds
so so let me start just with a funny
place you know which is laughter right
in the kind of classical deepest
understanding possible is actually a
faculty of perception so the oldest
Hebrew mystical text we have is called
the book of creation and it's about 470
words and it lists 12 faculties of sense
perception and the twelfth Faculty right
the highest one the twelfth is laughter
so what does it mean it laughter a
Faculty of sense perception it means it
allows us to understand a dimension of
reality that nothing else allows us to
understand just like taste gives me
something that touch doesn't give me
that hearing that seem so what is that
that laughter allows you to understand
all right laughter allows me both to
nullify right the apparent paradox
all right I'll nullify the the false
dichotomy right and left allows me to
hold paradox it's left eleven will hold
that paradox so laughter is that
critical Faculty of sense perception
when we stop laughing it's not just if
we take ourselves too seriously but we
actually get lost in one half of the
paradox which is always the source of
evil right evil always emerges from an
unhealthy era Docs where we absolute
eyes right one side right and in some
sense that the modern expression of that
is what we call today extremism all
right you know extremists feel better
when they wake up in the morning right
you're right because because extremists
don't have to hold paradox so you know
you just you take one side of an issue
let's give one example then to you
Barbara but just to make this kind of
just really just alive for people in the
most obvious way
so take abortion right so what's your
position are you pro-life or pro-choice
but but who's who listen was against
life who's against choice but each side
absolute size is once
refuses to old paradox and and then D
contextualizes their value from the
larger constellation of values and then
becomes an idolatry right at the altar
of that particular value in a non
paradoxical way which all produces some
version of evil so holding paradox and
and in the ultimate in the ontological
sense right you know is the the key to
evolution actually it's actually the
mechanism of evolution itself is it
believe it'll hold paradox in its
ontological form which is so that's it's
such a perfect way to end right this
series I'm just gorgeous you see I want
to just say how it makes it easier to do
this is it's a simple phrase the
overview perspective when there's a book
that was written by Frank white about
the astronauts and what happened when
they saw Earth from space as a whole and
they gave us the picture of ourselves as
a whole system now think of all the
paradoxes on earth think of all the
conflict think of all the separation
think of the animals hunting each other
but from that perspective it was whole
and I'm just wondering about this
paradox requiring an overview
perspective where you see it as whole
because as you were talking Daniel I was
realizing innately you have an overview
perspective you can't see this part of
the house of that part of the house but
when you're seeing the whole you have to
be outside the whole to some degree to
see it and context is always standing
slightly outside so I just wanted to ask
to what degree to standing outside even
like choice or pro-life if you stand
outside of it you see really both parts
of it you see the good in both parts and
you but you're not caught up in either
of them oh so overview holes to get a
whole system I believe you have to spend
outside of it and another phrase for
that is extatic
mmm isn't very nice that the word
ecstasy should be ecstatic that I'm
standing outside its extent
think of joy and I was just looking at
that trying to understand it in
relationship to what you are saying is
oh so let's play with that if I take an
overview perspective from that
perspective of the house so I take an
aerial photographic I definitely get a
sense of the big picture of the house
right I can see that it has a north side
and the south side nice I can see that
but it doesn't give me the pictures that
being on the ground looking at it or
inside of it wood it doesn't replace
those I actually have no idea what the
inside of the house looks like I don't
even have a clear perspective on the
front door there so I have a high-level
perspective it's important and
meaningful and all of the smaller
perspectives are also important and
meaningful and none of those give me the
perspective that zooming in with a
microscope and actually looking at the
you know molecular structure of
something in the wall there which is
part of the truth that it would and so
the overview that gives you all of that
can't happen in a single snapshot right
there is no snapshot there's no picture
that you can do but there's a way
there's a I actually like the term that
Ken Wilber uses integral methodological
pluralism is mouthful but pluralism
means there's all these pictures right
but there is a method to how to
integrate them that actually makes sense
right which is how do you tie those
pictures together and so the overview
perspective like if I look at Earth from
the astronaut point of view it gives me
a perspective that no point of view on
earth could give there's no point like
being on earth you can't get wow this
pale blue dot and yet the pale blue dot
perspective also doesn't replace getting
to look face to face with you right and
so so I see integrating being actually
trans perspective oh it's not any
perspective it's the ability to put the
perspectives together which is a purely
abstract function not a five sensory
function and that's that's fantastic I'm
teaching two things just immersing that
one barber then back to Daniel ecstatic
right ecstatic so we talked earlier
about how the unique self allows you to
transcend the paradox between autonomy
and communion but when you're when
you're in unique self you're in the
fullness of your aliveness that's
actually what ecstasy does
yeah when you're ecstatic actually
autonomy in communion again disappear
right that's it yeah I can see it
happening yeah right in ecstasy itself
right you're totally open and fully
yourself right and of course that's the
nature of sexuality in its ultimate
place sexuality holds paradox it is
that's why sexuality represents a higher
order of being it's why it teaches
arrows because in its very nature it
holds this higher order of being and of
course integral methodological pluralism
of course the key is development right
now you're seeing the entire you're
seeing the entire up and down you're the
second year of consciousness so you see
all the levels of consciousness yet
you're not in any of them and so
therefore all of the different methods
are plurally appropriate because they
all naturally fall in the right place
and they don't conflict with each other
even though they do because they're held
in a larger piece okay but let's just
make this really kind of bring totally
down to earth so let's take just because
you're up here with me and we're hanging
out on so you guys met each other right
how long did you meet each other maybe
10 years ago 10 years ago 10 years ago
2007 2007 okay so this is just so did
you choose to meet each other you're
getting into a conference about standing
in a lobby right so you didn't shoot did
you guys choose to kind of start to kind
of work together a little bit well the
minute we started to talk right I got
that he knew something that I would love
to know more uh so you chose I chose my
attraction right right right I just
almost attracted couldn't you say you
took mean it could have been a different
way he's setting you up about the nature
of will and determinism well well I I'm
not no I don't know what you're setting
me up for you actually it wasn't
effective right away right because there
was something in his genius right that
responded to something in my yearning
right that was instantly experienced
right and has been consistent throughout
right it continues today because it was
accurate right now I'm totally with you
and of course Daniels complete right in
this case I am setting you up
right but of course your butt your butt
you're done but your delightedly kind of
expressing it so elegantly and
beautifully you know whenever there's a
couple whether we're a threesome couple
or a twosome word twosome in you're a
twosome but let's even take a romantic
couple you ask her a romantic couple did
you choose each other well of course we
did well yet and they said they say they
didn't you say we had no one else would
go out with you
you know we chose each other and then
you asked them right could it have been
any different and at first they say yes
but if they're a true romantic couple at
some point they drop in to a deeper
level of consciousness and said Sidney
and Barbara did you choose each other
well yeah but could you have not been
together well of course not so that was
of course Krishnamurti choicelessness
right so it's just a place where we can
all find in our lives a place just to
access it directly and a real kind of
direct experience where we're choosing
but we're not choosing and they're both
radically true right and yet there's a
higher subtlety in which there's
something which is called choicelessness
which is beyond and accessing those
truths are part of the source code
change that we need and everything
changes particularism and universalism
effort not effort I mean I just listed
just for fun right I listed about 27 of
them here but I just is why administers
but there's the whole this is a source
go change
it's so exciting but you know when I was
attracted to Daniel in the lobby it
wasn't that like chose to be attracted I
simply was attracted because of the
nature of what he was saying
choicelessness it's choiceless but I
wouldn't use the word please Joyce less
because it wasn't related to choice you
know it's not it's not the choice or
choice less it was attraction that was I
would say he's simply based on mutual
relationship that I didn't choose or not
choose just was it just was right you
know
mark the topic of reconciling volition
and determinism right and is all the
questions that go with it is universe
fundamentally deterministic is
they're some fundamental in determinism
right there is does that relate to human
free will or not right I come from
quantum mechanics does it come from
complexity does it come from the
fundamentality of subject like these are
some of the deepest X's - the basis of
philosophy and ontology and what's so
interesting about it because these were
the questions that I drove myself most
insane over for much of my life and I
think most people that get real deep
into it do and if you read the great
debates recently between Sam Harris and
Dan Dennett on the topic you know Sam
says there's no such thing as free will
but there is consciousness and Dan
Dennett says well there's no such thing
as consciousness but there is freewill
and you know real interesting kind of
ways and and all of the best
philosophers disagree for the most part
and their perspectives are true right
and how those ones reconcile so it's
like where is the false dichotomy
where's the where's the 2d instead of 3d
kind of respective and it does come down
to agency and it comes to well who is
the self that is choosing versus the
nature of reality that is determined
right right and the idea of the
separation of the individual self that
has a volition and the nature of the
rest of the universe exterior and all
the whole ons interior that are
contributing to that separation ends up
being a big part of the false dichotomy
where yes this there are a lot of
mechanics external and internal to how
this thing occurs and this thing is an
emergent property that is different than
the sum of its parts
and so yes there is volition and that is
deep everything that happens has
deterministic elements that are part of
it right right yeah that's exactly right
I mean emergence understood that's
exactly an emergence changes everything
because because emergence when we really
get emergence then that whole
conversation changes without emergence
as ad Adam it's a different conversation
we promise by doing the written notes of
this we're gonna make this a little
clearer I think we just long pretty much
everybody for anyone who is interested
and obviously there's a whole rabbit
hole
here that we're gonna be having big
conversations on this skimming but yeah
Kaufman's works specifically Stewart
Kaufman's work and the nature of
emergence and the fundamental creativity
of universe and that laws themselves are
still emerging and what he calls killing
the galilean dream that deeply changed
the deterministic only model for me
where I was able to hold that that's
great no coffins fantastic let's let's
maybe finish with a wild story about
King David because you know what the
heck right so King David is this kind of
messianic figure and David you know the
famous story right that Leonard Cohen
likes to think about right you know and
I'm and that wonderful hallelujah song
so David's on the roof right he sees you
know but Sheba you know and you know he
winds up sleeping with her and he has
her hasn't been killed and it's a it's a
bad story so the way the way the Zohar
right the the 13th century mystical
tradition tells the story is that you
know in it's at this an elliptical
Aramaic text and it's trying to explain
why David is called to the gesture of
the king why is David laughing so the
text says because David says to God God
you don't believe it doesn't exist goes
to God test me test me and God says he's
sure you know and God's best Bill Cosby
voice right and you know David says you
know I'm sure I can pass any test and
God says I don't think you should do
this right and God says no no you know
David I want to do it so David goes up
to the roof sees but she even complete
bells the test right so they got you
know God says to David like you move the
whole thing I told you this was gonna
happen and David says well you said I
was gonna fail I said I was gonna pass
so of course I'm gonna listen to you
because your God and the text says
because of that David was called the
gesture of the camera which is it I read
that passage for a decade before I was
about and I kept reading that passage
for a decade you know time after time
and of course it's an ultimate con which
actually encapsulate everything we just
don't know you know
so blessings let us be the jest for the
King and hold the paradoxes of our live
thank you for being with us everyone
Barbara Daniel Wow beautiful